Henry Cabot Lodge Correspondence
Henry Cabot Lodge Correspondence
1877-1924
Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924.
0.5 linear ft.
Papers of the U.S. Senator, editor, author. Outgoing letters to William H. Coolidge, Edward A. Filene, Curtis Guild, Jr., R.U. Johnson, Harry B. Kirtland, William S. Kyle, J.S. Henley Luce, Stephen Luce, George H. Moses, W.T. Sedgwick, A.R. Turner, Frank E. Woodward, and others.
149139
Biographical History
Henry Cabot Lodge (1850-1924) was an author and editor, and a United States senator from Massachusetts.
Henry Cabot Lodge was born at Boston on 12 May 1850, the son of John Ellerton and Anna (Cabot) Lodge. After graduation from Harvard College with the class of 1871 and a year of travel, he entered the Harvard Law School, from which he graduated in 1874. Offered an assistant editorship of the North American Review, Lodge began a literary career whose products include biographies of Washington, Hamilton, Webster, and George Cabot, his great- grandfather, as well as several collections of essays and speeches and contributions to various periodicals. In 1876 he obtained his Ph.D. in political science, the first doctorate in that field awarded by Harvard.
His political career was initiated in 1879 by his successful candidacy for the Massachusetts House of Representatives from Nahant, which he represented for two terms. Failing in attempts to win a state Senate seat and a Republican nomination for Congress, he enhanced his political stature by successfully managing the 1883 Republican gubernatorial campaign in Massachusetts. Although defeated for Congress in 1884, his adherence to the Republican regulars made possible his nomination and election in 1886. During his terms in the House (1887-1893), he became known for his association with the Force Bill and his advocacy of civil-service reform.
Selected by the Massachusetts legislature as senator in 1893, he began his thirty-one- year service in the Senate, where he helped draft the Pure Food and Drug Law, displayed protectionist views on tariff matters, fought free silver, supported acquisition of the Philippines, and opposed women's suffrage and direct election of U.S. senators. He was re- elected to the Senate in 1899, 1905, 1911, 1916, and 1922. In the field of foreign affairs, Lodge held great influence during the Roosevelt presidency. In 1918 he was elected the majority leader of the Senate, and from the Foreign Relations Committee, of which he was chairman, he led opposition to the Peace Treaty and Covenant of the League of Nations. As the senior member of the Senate, he continued in his role of influence on foreign affairs during the Harding administration. Lodge married Anna Cabot Mills Davis; their children included George Cabot Lodge (1873-1902), the poet. Senator Lodge died at Cambridge on 9 November 1924.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Henry Cabot Lodge Correspondence contains 237 letters and two enclosures of printed material. Span dates are 1877 to 1924, although the years 1910 to 1922 are the most heavily represented. All letters save one are outgoing. The principal correspondents of Senator Lodge in this collection are John D. Henley Luce (69 letters), Stephen Bleecker Luce, naval officer and founder of the Naval War College (39 letters), and Curtis Guild, Jr. (14 letters). There are 108 other letters from Lodge to approximately 77 correspondents and six letters to unidentified correspondents. An index of the correspondence is appended to this inventory.
An enclosure in a note of 29 September 1908 is a Boston imprint of 1822, Defence of the exposition of the middling interest (Shoemaker 8523). The letters reflect constituents concerns on pending legislation. Subjects treated include tariff revision, child labor, national defense, the Corrupt Practices Act, sugar, Puerto Rico, arbitration commissions and treaties, the Spanish-American War, and World War I.
Arrangement of the Collection
Arrangement of the letters is chronological, and enclosures are filed with the letters they accompanied.
Related Material
See also the
Theodore Roosevelt Collection
for a bound, 400-page volume of typescript carbon copies of letters exchanged between Henry Cabot Lodge and Theodore Roosevelt from 1884 to 1917.
Subject and Genre Headings
Politics, government and public administration; Coolidge, William H.; Filene, E. A. (Edward Albert), 1860-1937.; Guild, Curtis, 1860-1915.; Johnson, Robert Underwood, 1853-1937.; Kirtland, Harry B.; Kyle, William S.; Lodge, Henry Cabot, 1850-1924.; Luce, John D. Henley.; Luce, Stephen Bleecker, 1827-1917.; Moses, George Higgins, 1969-1944.; Sedgwick, W. T. (William Thompson), 1855-1921.; Turner, A. R.; Woodward, Frank Ernest, 1853-1921.; Legislators -- United States.; Politicians -- United States.; United States -- Foreign relations -- 1865-1921.; United States -- Politics and government -- 1865-1933.; Legislators.; Politicians.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Purchase, 1962-1969.
Inventory
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1874-1878; 3 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1880-1885; 4 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1886-1889; 4 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1890; 7 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1891-1892; 7 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1893-1894; 7 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1897; 4 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1898; 8 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1899; 4 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1900; 7 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1901-1903; 4 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1904-1905; 10 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1907; 5 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1908-1909; 6 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1910; 12 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1911; 11 item (Box 1)
  - [General], 1912-1913; 10 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1914-1915; 11 item (Box 1)
  - [General], 1916; 19 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1917; 17 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1918; 16 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1919; 14 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1920; 9 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1921; 14 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1922; 9 items (Box 1)
  - [General], 1923-1924; 9 items (Box 1)
  - Partially dated, 5 items (Box 1)
  - Undated, 1 item (Box 1)
Index to correspondence
All correspondence is outgoing (from HCL) unless otherwise indicated.
Aimes, Mr. [ ] 1908 Sep 29, Nahant
Appleton, Francis H. 1903 Feb 27, [Washington]
Barrett, John 1919 Jan 7, Washington
Bieler, Frank I. 1917 Oct 26, Nahant
Brairelie, Anselino 1910 Mar 25, Washington
Brown, Mrs. Gilbert C. 1922 Sep 28, Washington
Brush, Dr. G.W. 1905 Feb 3, [Washington]
Bryce, [James] 1894 Nov 5, Nahant
Burbank, J.E. 1910 Apr 9, [Washington]
Butler, E.S. 1910 Mar 29, Washington
Chandler, Alice G. 1922 Jul 31, [Washington]
Coolidge, William H. 1910 Feb 25, [Washington] 1910 Mar 17, [Washington] 1910 Apr 5, Washington
Cousins, Mr. [ ] 1898 Sep 21, Nahant
Cox, Miss L.A. 1910 Apr 29, [Washington]
Davis, Hayne 1907 Feb 8, Washington
Day, Robert C. 1902 Jul 21, Nahant
Deane, Mr. [ ] 1878 Apr 19, Boston
Dickinson J[acob] M. (incoming) 1910 Feb 24, [Washington]
Douglass, Adeline A. 1911 Jun 13, [Washington]
Dwinnell, Clifton H. 1922 Feb 17, [Washington]
Ernst, Mr. [ ] 1899 Jan 16, Washington
Estes, Dana Jr. 1897 Jan 21, [Washington]
Fanning, Marshall B. 1897 Apr 8, Washington
Ferris, Morris P. 1897 Jan 20, [Washington]
Filene, Edward A. 1918 Sep 2, [Washington] 1924 Apr 18, [Washington]
Ford, Edward C. 1913 Sep 22, Nahant
Gallinger, Sen. [Jacob H.] 1908 Nov 23, [Washington]
Gardner, Charles W. 1889 Feb 7, Washington
Goss, Mr. [ ] 1898 Mar 7, Washington
Goss, E.H. 1904 Jul 13, Nahant
Graves, Edwfard] O. 1874 Aug 7, Nahant
Greenough, Charles P. n.y. Oct 29, [no place]
Gude, Mrs. Helen R. 1916 Dec 6, [Washington]
Guild, Col. Curtis, Jr. 1892 May 12, Washington 1892 May 24, Washington 1892 Dec 9, Washington 1892 Dec 10, Washington 1893 Mar 16, Washington 1901 May 23, [no place] 1901 Nov 4, Nahant 1904 Feb 27, [Washington] 1904 Apr 4, [Washington] 1904 Apr 19, [Washington] 1904 Dec 7, [Washington] 1905 Dec 4, [Washington] 1905 Dec 8, Washington n.y. Dec 11, Washington
Guild, Mrs. Curtis 1915 Apr 14, Washington
Hagedorn, Hermann 1921 Dec 12, [Washington]
Hall, Charles A. 1919 Sep 9, [Washington]
Hannum, F.A. 1916 Jan 31, [Washington]
Hartzell, Charles 1921 Aug 11, [Washington]
Hazeltine, Mr. 1899 Jan 12, Washington
Hickok, Rev. Paul R. 1919 Jan 11, [Washington]
Hintze, Thomas H. 1898 Nov 2, Nahant
Houghton, Mifflin & Co. 1898 Feb 5, Washington 1919 Jan 25, [Washington]
Howe, Walter C. 1918 Apr 5, [Washington]
Jenkins, E.L. 1890 Jan 13, Washington
Johnson, Mr. 1891 Mar 12, Washington
Johnson, R.U. 1924 Mar 11, [Washington] 1924 Apr 26, [Washington]
Jones, Rebecca 1910 Mar 30, [Washington]
Kilbreth, Mary G. 1924 Jan 23, [Washington]
Kirtland, Harry B. 1900 Sep 13, Nahant 1900 Oct 6, Nahant 1900 Oct 9, Nahant
Kyle, William S. 1898 Sep 23, Nahant 1909 Oct 5, Washington 1910 Dec 31, Washington 1921 Jul 15, Washington 1921 Aug 8, Washington
Luce, John D. Henley 1894 Aug 2, Washington [1894] Dec 4, Washington 1898 Mar 7, Washington 1898 Apr 9, Washington 1899 May 3, Rome 1907 Feb 7, [Washington] 1907 Dec 20, [Washington] 1907 Dec 25, [Washington] 1908 Feb 10, [Washington] 1909 Sep 14, [Boston] 1909 Oct 14, Nahant 1911 Jan 1, Washington 1911 Jan 20, Washington 1911 Jan 28, Washington 1911 Feb 22, [Washington] 1911 Apr 20, [Washington] 1911 Jun 1, [Washington] 1911 Dec 26, Washington 1912 Apr 25, [Washington] 1912 Jun 7, [Washington] 1912 Aug 1, Washington 1912 Aug 15, [Washington] 1912 Dec 26, [Washington] 1913 Apr 7, [Washington] 1913 Apr 24, [Washington] 1913 May 31, [Washington] 1913 Dec 29, Washington 1914 Feb 27, [Washington] 1914 Aug 29, [no place] 1915 Jan 13, [Washington] 1915 Feb 12, [Washington] 1915 Nov 30, Washington 1915 Dec 9, [Washington] 1915 Dec 11, [no place] 1915 Dec 22, [Washington] 1916 Apr 26, [Washington] 1916 May 10, [Washington] 1916 May 21, [n.p.] 1916 Jul 16, [no place] 1916 Dec 16, [Washington] 1916 Dec 25, Washington 1916 Dec 28, [Washington] 1917 Jan 3, [Washington] 1917 Jan 10, [Washington] 1917 Feb 5, [Washington] 1917 Feb 17, [Washington] 1917 Mar 7, [Washington] 1917 Jun 4, [Washington] 1917 Jun 6, [Washington] 1917 Jul 29, [Washington] 1917 Aug 6, Nahant 1917 Sep 28, Nahant 1918 Jan 19, Washington 1918 Feb 4, [Washington] 1918 Feb 7, [Washington] 1918 Feb 21, [Washington] 1918 Mar 30, [Washington] 1918 Apr 13, [no place] 1918 Aug 29, [Washington] 1918 Oct 9, [Washington] 1918 Oct 14, [Washington] 1919 Feb 14, [Washington] 1919 Jun 24, [Washington] 1919 Aug 18, [Washington] 1919 Aug 30, [Washington] 1920 Jan 21, [Washington] 1920 Feb 25, [Washington] 1920 May 12, [Washington] 1921 Jan 4, [Washington]
Luce, Stephen Bleecker 1915 Oct 21, Nahant 1915 Dec 25, [Washington] 1916 Apr 8, Washington 1916 Apr 11, [Washington] 1916 Apr 28, [Washington] 1916 May 4, [Washington] 1916 May 8, [Washington] 1916 [ca. Nov 8], Boston 1916 Dec 22, [Washington] 1916 Dec 29, [Washington] 1917 Jan 4, [Washington] 1917 Feb 3, [Washington] 1917 Apr 11, [Washington] 1917 Apr 13, [Washington] 1917 Apr 18, [Washington] 1918 Mar 22, [Washington] 1918 Mar 25, [Washington] 1918 Mar 29, [Washington] 1918 Apr 3, [Washington] 1919 Dec 26, [Washington] 1919 Dec 29, [Washington] 1920 Nov 29, [Washington] 1921 Jan 19, [Washington] 1921 Feb 2, [Washington] 1921 Feb 23, [Washington] 1921 Mar 25, [Washington] 1921 May 14, [Washington] 1921 May 19, [Washington] 1921 Oct 13, [Washington] 1921 Dec 26, [Washington] 1922 Jan 3, [Washington] 1922 Jan 11, [Washington] 1922 May 22, [Washington] 1922 Jun 7, Boston 1922 Nov 13, Nahant 1924 Jan 31, [Washington] 1924 Aug 9, [Boston] n.y. Dec 20, [Washington] n.d., [no place] [memorandum requesting admittance of Stephen B. Luce to see Admiral Palmer]
MacQueen, Peter 1917 Mar 28, [Washington]
McCann, Commodore W.P. 1889 Nov 11, Washington
Megrew, Mrs. John P. 1919 Mar 15, [Washington]
Moody, Dean [ ] n.y. Apr 30, [no place]
Moses, Sen. George H. 1919 Oct 8, [Washington] 1920 Aug 16, Nahant 1921 Apr 18, [Washington] 1924 Mar 14, [Washington]
Munro, David A. 1904 Jul 30, Nahant
National Cash Register Co. 1922 Feb 8, [Washington]
Newcomb, H.T. 1907 Feb 16, [Washington]
Nichols, George D. 1910 Mar 23, [Washington]
Norris, Mr. 1898 Aug 8, Nahant n.y. Mar 9, [Boston]
Olcott, [ ] 1880 Sep 19, Nahant
Orlandini, Vittorio 1920 Apr 29, [Washington]
Orth, John 1919 Oct 3, [Washington]
Parker, Mr. and Mrs. 1890 May 6, Washington
Prang, Mrs. Louis 1910 Mar 30, [Washington]
Putnam, Capt. Eben 1919 Sep 11, [Washington]
Putnam, George] H. 1891 Mar 11, [Washington]
Sedgwick, Prof. W.T. 1900 Dec 24, Washington
Sedgwick, W.T. 1918 Sep 4, [Washington]
Shepard, John 1920 Jan 1, [Washington]
Stetson, W. Graydon 1916 Apr 17, Washington
Taggard, Henry 1923 Oct 23, Nahant
Turner, A.R., Jr. 1890 Mar 19, [no place] 1890 Jun 10, [no place] 1890 Jun 22, [no place] 1890 Dec 9, [no place] 1891 Mar 9, [no place] 1911 Dec 1, [no place] 1911 Dec 1, [no place] 1911 Dec 5, [no place]
Warfield, E.D. 1893 Mar 24, Washington
Watson, Caroline A. 1920 Sep 20, Nahant
Woodward, Mr. 1894 Dec 3, Washington 1894 Dec 21, Washington
Woodward, Frank E. 1920 May 6, [Washington]
Worthington, Mr. [ 1884 Oct 25, Boston
Wright, Samuel C. 1905 Jan 14, Washington
Young, Benjamin Loring 1916 Jul 1, [Washington]
[ ,] Louisa ("Isa") 1877 Jul 17, [no place] 1897 Dec 31, Washington 1899 Nov 19, Washington 1900 Mar 4, Washington 1900 Mar 14, Washington 1900 May 12, Washington
Unidentified "Sir" 1884 Dec 16, [Boston] "My dear Sir" 1885 Mar 14, Boston "My dear Sir" 1886 Nov 24, [no place] "Dear Sir" 1887 Apr 24, [Washington] "My dear Sir" 1890 Nov 20, Washington "My dear Sir" 1924 Jan 21, [Washington]